Now for Task 12.
We should implement a function that checks if some
Integer is not present in a list of Integers.
So if this Integer v is not
an element of this list xs.
Okay, so again, we should only use one
equation, maybe with guards, to do this.
And we have some test cases
given that we should fulfill.
How do we do this?
Let's start with adding some
guards to distinguish some cases.
The first case checks if head
xs is actually equivalent to v.
If this is the case, we found v in
the list, so we return False, right?
This is the simplest thing we can think of.
Okay, so what happens if this is not the case?
Well, if the head element is not the element
we are looking for, or not looking for,
then we should look in the rest of the
list if this element is not present there.
So we do notElem on the tail of xs.
And we should also give it the
element we are not looking for.
Okay, so does this work?
Well, probably not, but let's try it anyway.
So let's say we're looking
for whether 1 is not in [1].
Well, we get the correct answer there.
Let's see if 1 is not in the list [2,5,1,6].
notElem is also giving the right answer there.
So our base case and our recursion seem to work.
Okay, let's try a negative example.
What if it's actually not in the list?
Well, we're trying to get
the head of an empty list.
So this is because we forgot to handle
the case that the list could be empty.
So if the list is empty, what's our result?
Well, no element is present in
the empty list, so we return True
if we check that v is not in the empty list.
Okay, so this gives us a base case in the
negative, or in this case positive, case.
So notElem 1 [2,5,6] now returns True.
Okay, let's check that it also fulfills
this test suite we're given here.
Looks good.
So what do we actually test here?
We test that
if we call notElem x [] we should always get
True no matter what element we choose (for x).
This is why we added this case,
because this should be the
base case of the recursion.
For a singleton list [x] we
can always say that if we try
notElem x [x] we should always get False.
And therefore we use not here because we always
state true facts in these QuickCheck tests.
Okay, then [y] does not contain
x, if x and y are different.
This is how we write this in QuickCheck.
This also seems like a logical
thing to do or to test.
And then we test that a combined
list does not contain an element v
exactly if it is not contained in one of the
lists from which the combined list is made.
So if we have a list xs and a list
ys, then checking whether v is not
an element of the combination of these two lists
is the same as checking whether it's not
an element of xs and not an element of ys.
Then it is also not an
element of the combination.
Okay, this is what these tests do.
And we more or less do, at least for the first few
tests; we can see that these are our cases here.
Okay, so is there another way to solve this?
Sure, for example, we can realize that we
are actually dealing with Booleans here.
So on this side we have Boolean values,
and here we have Boolean values,
so we can rewrite this using Boolean connectives.
So, instead of these guards, let's say in one
Boolean expression what notElem really is.
So we have the first condition here that says it's
true if xs is null, so you can just write null xs.
And then we add the second condition.
And if we look carefully at these
two conditions we see that this is
(head xs /= v) && (notElem v (tail xs))
This just says in one expression without any
guards, that either the list is empty or
the first element is different from v and the rest
of the list also does not contain the element.
And that's the definition of what it means
for v to not be an element of this list.
Okay, this is possible because we are
dealing with a Boolean valued output.
And we can use these (&&) and (||)
connectives to write a thing like this.
And sometimes you would prefer this version
with guards over this expression, and
sometimes, depending on the context, this
single expression might be favorable.
But there's another solution that is
interesting, maybe a bit more declarative.
We use the observation that ...
If v is not an element of xs then there
are no elements in xs that are equal to v.
This means that if we take all the
elements of xs via a list comprehension,
and only take those that are equal to v,
then we get all the elements that
are equal to v in that list and
for an element to not be in the
list, this list now has to be empty.
This says if there is no element in xs
such that x == v, then v is not in xs.
This is a nice declarative alternative to this
Boolean expression with recursion, because
as you can see, there’s no recursion here.
And this is also correct as we
can see by running the tests.
(Maybe we should save it
first and now run the tests.)
It passes all the tests,
but it’s way harder to see by looking at
the code that it fulfills these properties.
But we can run them and then verify
that this actually works out.
This is a nice observation that we can make here
to get this solution with list comprehensions.